Not as important as
uh
to not have ill will is.
So, I think that's all That's pretty
much the the reason why people would be
thinking about forgiveness and so on.
It's because of the ill will.
So, ill will is a problem.
And the only way for you to know how to
not have ill will is to forgive. But
But
forgiveness is not necessary
in order for ill will to not be.
In other words, you can not have ill
will and not forgive. So, you forgive,
but not foolishly pretend that it never
happened. If it's something of of of of
thing that you
that's actually beneficial for you to
not forget.
Like, you know, when the Buddha would
say you should reflect what type of people
you should reflect what type of people
you're associating with.
Don't just indiscriminately indiscriminately
sort of
make friendships and and and when some
people are simply not good for you or or
not good for themselves or others,
unwholesome. So, you want to use the reflection
So, you want to use the reflection
intelligence even when you basically
choose friends.
So, if there is something that's that's
uh you want to forgive, yeah, by all
means.
You don't have to hold a grudge or have
ill will towards that person.
So, if if that's what's meant by
forgiveness, then yeah.
It's important to not have ill will. So,
it's important to forgive.
But if by forgiveness it's meant, "Oh,
it's important to pretend like it never
happened or like it will never happen
again." No, that's just foolish.
That's not really the forgiveness you
should be practicing
or or trying to develop.
So, you don't want to lose your
intelligence discernment and see like
what is the likelihood of this person
doing this again?
And your reason will tell you. You already
your reason will tell you. You already
know the answer.
So, if it's a high likelihood that
whatever you're required to forgive will
be repeated
yeah, okay, I will not bear a grudge. I
will not have ill will, but I don't want
to have to go through this again because
I don't see any change
in the behavior of that person. So, it's
most likely going to happen again.
And thus, from that point of view,
you're not you're not
you're not ignoring it.
So, you're not forgiving it, so to
speak. And you don't need to forgive it as long
And you don't need to forgive it as long
as you don't hate them on account of it.
So, what what you what you want to see
then is what is up to you.
Whether others others forgive you or
not, that's not up to you. And you have
no right to demand forgiveness.
But what is up to you is to see what led
up to the
basically result of needing forgiveness
of others. Your actions.
So, if you want to be forgiven
or rather if you don't want to be in a
position that you will have to be
forgiven again
uh start reflecting upon your actions
and your thoughts and your speech. Stop
being careless. The true repentance
would be then changing your ways.
So, that you will not
uh end up in a position again
whereby you will need others to forgive you.
So, that's what I meant.
Like whether you are you you are the one
whether you are you you are the one
forgiving or you need to be forgiven
you don't want to just okay, forgiveness
means let's just pretend it never
happened. Forgiveness means like, well,
let's see if this will happen again.
So, is this person really making a
change in their ways so they will not do
this again or they're just trying to
make me believe that they are. But what
is the likelihood of that?
So, even if they yes, they're trying to
make you believe they're going to change
their way
you you accept that, you give them the
benefit of the doubt, but it doesn't
mean you forget. You pretend like it
never happened. Don't forget. Don't lose
the context on certain behavior.
And the same goes for you. If you want
to be forgiven
it's easy to be inspired to change your
ways when there is basically
unforgiving people around you and you
feel bad for what you've done and
they're not forgiving you and you feel
horrible. Yeah, it's easy then to
inspire and make promises.
But that that kind of um
that that kind of um
adverse
pressure will will fade. So, it can't
last forever.
So, will you be able to then keep your
promises of your changed ways
after that? Will you still be able to
Oh, yeah, but no, this is still the
right thing to do or not?
So, if you really truly want to be
forgiven and if you truly want to not
end up in a position where you would
need to be forgiven
you need to start
uh
using your reason and your intellect for
criteria for your action, not your
emotions. Cuz see, because you were careless,
Cuz see, because you were careless,
acting out of how you felt, not really
thinking through, you ended in a
position of hurting other people.
Now they need to forgive you. Now when
you're so desperate for forgiveness,
that's another emotion, another
unpleasant state that you really can't
get want to get rid of. So, you're
equally not reasonable even when you
made your make your promises that you
are a changed man and so on.
You're still acting out of your emotions
and they are unpredictable.
And they are unreasonable
by definition. So.
So, the true repentance then is for the
one who goes beyond carelessness.
Beyond acting out of how you feel,
beyond acting out of craving how you
feel. As I said people are most more
often than not truly sorry for what
they've done, but it doesn't mean that
in the long run they will change their
ways. They're simply under the pressure of
They're simply under the pressure of
that bad feeling of their action, you
know, what they've done and so on.
They're aware of it, but will they
change their way? Well, you see that
after that feeling is gone. Are they
still acting the same, carelessly
pretending like it never happened or
truly making the effort?
So, there's no guarantee that the person
will will change their ways, but and
there is no guarantee for you that you
can tell at that stage. You can only see
that later on. That's what I mean. You
if you are the one doing the forgiving,
yeah, you can forgive in terms of don't
have ill will, but do not forget
that things can be repeated.
[Music] Especially if the evidence shows you
Especially if the evidence shows you
that.
So, it doesn't mean like, "Oh, I will
hate you forever." It simply means like,
"Oh, I will be careful whenever I engage
with you so I don't end up in a position
I need to forgive you again."
Because your actions created that.
And if somebody demands from you that
you must pretend it never happened and
just just let's just
let's just ignore this cuz that's the
true forgiveness. It's not. They're just
basically asking you to forsake your
intellect so that they will feel better.